<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter id="installation">
  <title>Installation</title>   
       
	<para> 
	This section describes the installation procedure for SAVARA tools and runtime modules.
	</para>
       
       <section>
       		<title>Prerequisites</title>
       		<para>
       		The pre-requisites for the SAVARA Eclipse Tools are:
       		</para>
       		<orderedlist>
       			<listitem>Eclipse JEE (3.6 or higher)  <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org">http://www.eclipse.org</ulink></listitem>
       			<listitem>JBoss Tools (3.2 or higher) <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/tools">http://www.jboss.org/tools</ulink>
       			available from an update site</listitem>
       		</orderedlist>

       		<para>
       		The pre-requisites for the SAVARA JBoss server integration are:
       		</para>
       		<orderedlist>
       			<listitem>JBossAS (5.1.0.GA or higher) <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/jbossas">http://www.jboss.org/jbossas</ulink></listitem>
       			<listitem>JBossAS (4.8 or higher) <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/jbossesb">http://www.jboss.org/jbossesb</ulink></listitem>
       			<listitem>SAVARA (version 2.0.0 or higher), available from <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/savara/downloads">http://www.jboss.org/savara/downloads</ulink></listitem>
       		</orderedlist>
       </section>
       
       <section>
       		<title>Installation Instructions</title>
       		<para>
       		The installation instructions for the SAVARA Eclipse tools are:
       		</para>
       		<orderedlist>
       			<listitem>
       			Eclipse
       			<para>
       			Download the latest version of Eclipse JEE, and install in your environment.
       			</para>
       			</listitem>
       			
       			<listitem>
       			BPMN Modeller
       			<para>
       			When Eclipse has been lauched, go to the <emphasis>Help->Install New Software..</emphasis>
       			menu item. Select the Eclipse update site
       			for the version of Eclipse (e.g. Helios). Within the SOA Development
       			category, select the BPMN Project Feature. Follow the instructions to accept
       			the license and then restart Eclipse after the plugins have been
       			installed.
       			</para>
       			</listitem>
       			<listitem>
       			JBoss Tools
       			<para>
       			Start up your Eclipse environment, and go to the <emphasis>Help->Install New Software..</emphasis>
       			menu item. Select the appropriate update site URL from the JBoss Tools download
       			page, and enter it into the top text field in the dialog window, and press the
       			<emphasis>Add</emphasis> button. Once the contents of the update site is available,
       			then select the appropriate components and follow the instructions to install
       			them within your Eclipse environment.
       			</para>
       			<para>
       			The <emphasis>JBoss Savara Tools</emphasis> feature should be selected from the
       			<emphasis>SOA Development</emphasis> category.
       			</para>
       			<para>
       			If you wish to view the generated BPEL using a BPEL editor, rather than
       			XML, then you should also select the <emphasis>JBoss BPEL Editor</emphasis> from the
       			<emphasis>SOA Development</emphasis> category.
       			</para>
       			<para>
       			NOTE: If you don't install the BPEL Editor, then you will have to install
       			GMF. This can be found on the Helios update site, under the <emphasis>Modeling</emphasis>
       			category. Select the <emphasis>Graphical Modeling Framework</emphasis> entry, and
       			following the instructions to install.
       			</para>

       			<para>
       			It is also recommended that you install the JBoss WebServices Tools, and JBossAS Tools,
       			from the All category. These are required to define and launch a JBossAS
       			server from within Eclipse, generate a JAX-WS web service from a WSDL definition,
       			and test a Web Service.
       			</para>
       			</listitem>

       		</orderedlist>

       		<para>
       		The installation instructions for the SAVARA JBoss server integration are:
       		</para>
       		<orderedlist>
       			<listitem>
       			JBossAS
       			<para>
       			Download the latest version and follow its installation instructions.
       			</para>
       			</listitem>
       			
       			<listitem>
       			JBossESB
       			<para>
       			Download the latest version and follow the instructions for installing it
       			into the JBossAS environment.
       			</para>
       			</listitem>
       			
       			<listitem>
       			SAVARA
       			<para>
       			Unpack the SAVARA distribution and edit the
       			<filename>deployment.properties</filename> file
       			in this <filename>${SAVARA}/install</filename> folder.
       			Set the <emphasis>org.jboss.as.home</emphasis> property to the root
       			directory where the JBossAS environment is located, and change the
       			<emphasis>org.jboss.as.config</emphasis> property from default
       			if you wish to start your JBossAS using a different configuration. Set the
       			<emphasis>org.jboss.esb.home</emphasis> property to the root directory
       			where the JBossESB environment is located.
       			</para>
       			<para>
       			Start a command window and execute the command <emphasis>ant deploy</emphasis>.
       			</para>
       			</listitem>

       		</orderedlist>
       </section>

	<section>
		<title>Importing Samples into Eclipse</title>

			<para>
		Once the SAVARA Eclipse Tool distribution has been correctly installed, if you wish to try out 
		any of the examples then the following steps should be followed to import the relevant
		projects into the previously configured Eclipse environment.
			</para>

  <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
		<para>
Select the 'Import...' menu item, associated with the popup menu on the background of the left 
panal (Navigator or Package depending on perspective being viewed).
		</para>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="en-US/images/ImportMenu.jpg" align="center" width="2in" />
		</imageobject>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>
When the import dialog appears, select the <emphasis>General->ExistingProject from Workspace</emphasis> 
option and press the 'Next' button.
		</para>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="en-US/images/ImportDialog.jpg" align="center" width="4in" />
		</imageobject>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>
Ensuring that the 'Select root directory' radio button is selected, press the 'Browse' button and 
navigate to the <filename>${SAVARA-Tools}/samples</filename> folder, then press 'Ok'.
		</para>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="en-US/images/ImportFileDialog.jpg" align="center" width="3in" />
		</imageobject>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>
All of the Eclipse projects contained within the <filename>${SAVARA-Tools}/samples</filename> directory structure 
will be listed. Press the 'Finish' button to import them all.
		</para>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="en-US/images/ImportProjectsDialog.jpg" align="center" width="4in" />
		</imageobject>
		<para>
		Once imported, the Eclipse navigator will list the sample projects:
		</para>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="en-US/images/ImportedProject.jpg" align="center" width="2in" />
		</imageobject>
	</listitem>
     </orderedlist>

	</section>
  
</chapter>
